Umang Desai

(703) 980-3493 | umangd03@gmail.com | www.umangdesai.com

Summary

Hands on, versatile engineer with an eye for simplicity and elegance in the software I write; looking for full time opportunities. I recently achieved my Masters in Computer Science before which I was a software engineer for 4 years, working out of Silicon Valley.

Education

M.S Computer Science	2016-2018
George Mason University	GPA: 3.4

B.S Information Science and Technology

Pennsylvania State University

2008-2012

GPA: 3.0

Coursework: Operating Systems, Distributed Systems, Analysis of Algorithms, Advanced Database Systems, Software Testing, Program Design and Data Structures, Component Based Software Development, Software Modeling and Architecture, Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science.

Skills

Languages: JAVA, C++, C, Python

Frameworks/Environments: Junit4.0, JSF, Apache Camel, XStream, log4j, AWS

Operating Systems: Linux, Windows, OSX

Database Systems & Servers: MS-SQL, MySQL, TOMCAT, Windows ISS

IDEs & Version Control: Eclipse, Netbeans, PyCharm, GIT, SVN

Work Experience

George Mason Univ. Department of Computer Science

Aug 2017 - Current

Graduate Teaching Assistant (Software Engineering)

- Conducting lectures and presentations.
- *Grading* deliverables for a full scale SDLC project, assignments, presentation peer evaluations.
- *Mentoring* students on different stages of SDLC and conducting bi-weekly meetings for project review, enabling AGILE culture.

Matreya.IO Jun 2017 – Jul 2017

Blockchain Developer

- Develop and review high level design for the BlockChain. Also, find possible implementation solutions for Proof of Space(PoS).
- Optimize Proof of Work algorithm for x86.
- Modify difficulty adjustment algorithm to DigiByte v3.0.
- Designed and tested unit tests for DAA and PoW algorithms.

George Mason Univ. Department of Computer Science

Jan 2017 - May 2017

Graduate Teaching Assistant (Object Oriented Programming)

- *Mentoring* undergraduates through office hours, teaching students of varying level of understanding the *concepts of Java Object Oriented Programming*.
- Conducting lectures and programming labs.
- *Grading* assignments, labs, projects.

Fondo Jan 2015 – Mar 2016

Co-Founder

- Social event discovery application to correlate user and events geospatial data and indicate suitable local events for a user.
- Designing and developing backend, databases and data-models.
- Maintain, monitor and *review development* of the application and *manage project deadlines*.
- Actively involved in *software architecture and product development*.

ESQ Business Services

Aug 2012 - Dec 2014

Software Engineer

- Designed, developed and tested module to *monitor JVM* on a host by *extracting telemetry data* using *JAVA*, *MSSQL* and *JMX*. This was achieved via a 3 tier *client-server-data backend architecture*.
- Designed and modeled a database for the data extracted. Then *developed advanced filtering* across *multiple Mbeans* for retrieving these metrics for *bandwidth friendly data pipelines*.
- Configured frameworks like *XStream* for configuration files and models, *log4j* for logging.
- Designed, developed and tested module to *monitor Linux via the proc fs to analyze system performance and uptime.* This was achieved with *JAVA and MSSQL*
- Developed a parsing framework for system proc files with configurable polling mechanisms.

Personal Projects

Content Addressable Network

• Built a *scalable distributed hash table network* using JAVA, RMI. The idea is to help manage a large hash table over internet like scalability. This can also support distributed data storage.

Operating System

• Operating systems fundamental development. Implemented OS concepts like *synchronization* primitives, process creation, multi-processing, virtual memory. Development was done using *C*, gcc and vi.

NFL Fantasy League Software Model & Architecture

• Gathered requirements and built use cases. Use UML to design the static/dynamic class structures, sequence diagrams, state machines.

Two-Phase Commit Transaction System

• A *distributed durable* key/value store which supports *two-phase commit protocol*. It is *scalable* in that it supports multiple clients being able to connect to the master and issue a stream of get/put/del requests.